Phone: 617-901-6636 Email: <u>lalit.89@live.com</u> Webpage: <u>Website</u> / <u>LinkedIn</u>

International economist with expertise in empirical and quantitative research. Experienced as a data scientist, an economic theorist, a technical instructor, with additional skills in healthcare and financial analysis.

Professional Experience

Doctoral candidate, Department of Economics, Boston University (2016-present)

- Executed end-to-end projects in international economics, and macroeconomics, including research design, data collection, empirical analysis, and result interpretation.
- Quantified the impact of travel-costs on international trade using novel data and model and showed that easier access to visas can increase trade between EU and China by 1.3% and EU output by 0.73%.
- Identified a robust positive relationship between firm-size and information technology adoption using a unique factory-level time-series on computer and software equipment in India.
- Applied causal inference methods in quasi-experimental settings including diff-in-diff, and instrumental variable.
- Developed and validated mathematical models of economic behavior to simulate changes in policies and technologies and predict changes key economic outcomes.

Teaching fellow, Center for Data Science/Department of Economics, Boston University (2017-2018, 2021-present)

- Designed and delivered lectures for 3+ years on linear algebra, probability theory, optimization methods, and statistics and econometrics to over 500 students.
- Introduced fundamental concepts and tools in data science including k-NN classification, neural networks, decision trees, regularization, and stochastic gradient descent.
- Taught programming with Jupyter for Python, RMarkdown for R, and Stata for data processing and visualization, and econometric analysis.

Short term consultant, World Bank, Washington D.C. (Summer 2019)

• Proposed a new measurement of poverty using realistic household demand to account for non-food consumption; highlighted the relevance of price index with simulations.

Investment Banking analyst/associate, UBS-Verity Knowledge Solutions, India (2011-2014)

- Created detailed pitch decks for M&A advisory for the global healthcare markets including market research, firm valuations, target screening, and due diligence; assisted the team that closed the \$7.3bn Coventry-Aetna merger.
- Communicated with clients, delivered on tight timelines, coordinated with team members, and mentored juniors.

Education

Ph.D. (Economics), Boston University, 2024 (Expected in December)

• Graduate student fellowship (2016-2022)

M.Sc. (Quantitative Economics), Indian Statistical Institute (New Delhi, India), 2016

• First class with distinction (76%); Merit scholarship (top 5 position in the cohort).

B.Tech. (Biotechnology), National Institute of Technology (Warangal, India), 2011

• First class with distinction (8.46/10); Indian Academy of Science Summer Fellowship (2010)

Technical skills

- Scripting languages and statistical packages: Python, R, MATLAB, and Stata. Version control with GitHub.
- Documenting: LaTeX, Markdown, MS word and PowerPoint.
- Project management: Trello, Slack.